阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 校：@Auriance 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组
大家好 我是凯莉·安 这是计算机速成课
Hi, I'm Carrie Anne, this is Crash Course Computer Science,
今天我们讨论处理器
and today, we're talking about processors.
只是提醒一下 这可能是这一系列中最难的一集
Just a warning though - this is probably the most complicated episode in the series.
所以当你看到这就很了不起了
So once you get this, you're golden.
我们已经制造出了算数和逻辑单元 它以二进制数为输入
We've already made an Arithmetic and Logic Unit, which takes in binary numbers
进行计算 我们还制造了两种计算机存储器
and performs calculations, and we've made two types of computer memory:
寄存器 线性的小存储器只能用来储存单个数值
Registers -- small, linear chunks of memory, useful for storing a single value
然后我们把它叠加制成了随机访问存储器RAM
and then we scaled up, and made some RAM,
这是一种更大的可以存放许多不同地址的数字的记忆储存
a larger bank of memory that can store a lot of numbers located at different addresses.
现在该把它们结合到一起搭建所有计算机的心脏
Now it's time to put it all together and build ourselves the heart of any computer,
但是没有人类内心的感情
but without any of the emotional baggage that comes with human hearts.
对计算机来说 这是中央处理器 通常叫做CPU
For computers, this is the Central Processing Unit, most commonly called the CPU.
CPU的工作是执行程序
A CPU's job is to execute programs.
像是微软办公 safari浏览器 或你最爱的半条命2游戏这样的程序
Programs, like Microsoft Office, Safari, or your beloved copy of Half Life: 2,
都是由一系列单独的操作组成 叫做指令
are made up of a series of individual operations, called instructions,
因为他们指挥计算机去做什么
because they “instruct” the computer what to do.
如果是数学指令 如加法和减法
If these are mathematical instructions, like add or subtract,
CPU会设置它的ALU进行数学运算
the CPU will configure its ALU to do the mathematical operation.
或者是存储指令
Or it might be a memory instruction,
这时CPU会用到存储器去读写数据
in which case the CPU will talk with memory to read and write values.
CPU有很多组分 所以我们会一步一步的设计
There are a lot of parts in a CPU, so we're going to lay it out piece by piece,
同时进行搭建
building up as we go.
我们会关注于功能块而不是展示每一条线路
We'll focus on functional blocks, rather than showing every single wire.
当把两个部件用线连接起来时
When we do connect two components with a line,
这就是进一步的抽象
this is just another level of abstraction.
这一层高级的视角叫做微结构
This high level view is called the microarchitecture.
首先我们需要一些存储器
OK, first, we're going to need some memory.
我们进入上一集中的RAM模块
Let's drop in the RAM module we created last episode.
为了简化 我们假设它只有16个储存位置 每一个容纳8比特位
To keep things simple, we'll assume it only has 16 memory locations, each containing 8 bits.
并且给处理器加上4个8位的存储寄存器 标号为A B C D
Let's also give our processor four, 8-bit memory registers, labeled A, B, C and D
用来临时储存和操作数值
which will be used to temporarily store and manipulate values.
我们已经知道数据可以以二进制存在存储器中
We already know that data can be stored in memory as binary values
程序也可以存在存储器中
and programs can be stored in memory too.
我们可以为每个CPU支持的指令分配一个身份编号ID
We can assign an ID to each instruction supported by our CPU.
假设下 我们用前四位储存操作码
In our hypothetical example, we use the first four bits to store the “operation code”,
简写为opcode
or opcode for short.
后四位表明待运算的数来自哪里
The final four bits specify where the data for that operation should come from -
可能是寄存器或者是存储器的地址
this could be registers or an address in memory.
我们需要额外两个寄存器来完善CPU
We also need two more registers to complete our CPU.
首先需要一个寄存器记录执行到程序的哪一步
First, we need a register to keep track of where we are in a program.
为此我们使用指令地址寄存器 正如名字表明的
For this, we use an instruction address register, which as the name suggests,
它当前指令的存储地址
stores the memory address of the current instruction.
接着需要另一个寄存器存储当前的指令
And then we need the other register to store the current instruction,
我们把它叫做指令寄存器
which we'll call the instruction register.
当初始化计算机时 所有的寄存器以0开始
When we first boot up our computer, all of our registers start at 0.
举个例子 我们在RAM里预置一个简单的计算机程序
As an example, we've initialized our RAM with a simple computer program
接下来会执行一遍
that we'll go through today.
CPU运行的第一个阶段叫做读取阶段
The first phase of a CPU's operation is called the fetch phase.
【注：几乎所有的冯•诺伊曼型计算机的CPU，其工作都可以分为5个阶段：
1.取指令 2.指令译码 3.执行指令 4.访存+取数 5.结果写回】
这一阶段我们检索第一条指令
This is where we retrieve our first instruction.
首先 把指令地址寄存器连接到RAM模块
First, we wire our Instruction Address Register to our RAM module.
寄存器的数值是0 所以RAM返回地址0储存的数值
The register's value is 0, so the RAM returns whatever value is stored in address 0.
本例中是00101110
In this case, 0010 1110.
接着这个数值拷贝到指令寄存器中
Then this value is copied into our instruction register.
我们已经检索到了存储器中的指令
Now that we've fetched an instruction from memory,
就需要弄清这个指令是什么
we need to figure out what that instruction is
才能执行它
so we can execute it.
以便执行指令
是运行 不是处决它
That is run it. Not kill it.
【注：execute既有“执行”，也有“行刑”之意】
这阶段叫做破译阶段
This is called the decode phase.
本例中操作码 即前4位 是0010
In this case the opcode, which is the first four bits, is: 0010.
这个操作码对应 LOAD A 指令
This opcode corresponds to the “LOAD A” instruction,
即把RAM中的数值载入到寄存器A中
which loads a value from RAM into Register A.
RAM的地址是后4位 1110 或是十进制的14
The RAM address is the last four bits of our instruction which are 1110, or 14 in decimal.
接着指令由控制单元破解说明
Next, instructions are decoded and interpreted by a Control Unit.
与其他所有我们构建的元件 控制单元也是由逻辑门组成的
Like everything else we've built, it too is made out of logic gates.
例如 要识别LOAD A指令 需要一个电路检查
For example, to recognize a LOAD_A instruction, we need a circuit that checks
是否操作码与0010一致 这用一堆逻辑门就能检验
if the opcode matches 0010 which we can do with a handful of logic gates.
现在已经知道指令是什么了
Now that we know what instruction we're dealing with,
我们可以前进去执行这个指令 也就开始了执行阶段
we can go ahead and perform that instruction which is the beginning of the execute phase!
通过LOAD_A检查电路的输出
Using the output of our LOAD_A checking circuit,
开启RAM的读取电路并发送到地址14
we can turn on the RAM's read enable line and send in address 14.
RAM获取这个地址的数值00000011（十进制3）
The RAM retrieves the value at that address, which is 00000011, or 3 in decimal.
因为是LOAD_A指令
Now, because this is a LOAD_A instruction,
我们只把它保存在寄存器A中 其他的不变
we want that value to only be saved into Register A and not any of the other registers.
所以如果我们吧RAM的数据线路接到4个数据寄存器
So if we connect the RAM's data wires to our four data registers,
可以通过LOAD_A的检查电路只开启寄存器A的写入电路
we can use our LOAD_A check circuit to turn on the write enable only for Register A.
这样就成功了 把RAM地址14的数值放入寄存器A
And there you have it - we’ve successfully loaded the value at RAM address 14 into Register A.
完成了指令后 就可以关闭所有的电路
We've completed the instruction, so we can turn all of our wires off,
准备好检索存储器中下一条指令了
and we're ready to fetch the next instruction in memory.
要进入下一条 我们把指令地址寄存器加1
To do this, we increment the Instruction Address Register by 1
便完成了执行阶段
which completes the execute phase.
LOAD_A只是CPU能执行的众多指令中的一个
LOAD_A is just one of several possible instructions that our CPU can execute.
不同的指令用不同的逻辑电路破译
Different instructions are decoded by different logic circuits,
逻辑电路配置CPU的部件去执行这个行动
which configure the CPU's components to perform that action.
这些破译电路内部有过多的细节
Looking at all those individual decode circuits is too much detail,
所以既然我们看过了一个例子
so since we looked at one example,
那就向前进而把他们封装起来
we've going to go head and package them all up
作为一个单独的控制单元使问题简单
as a single Control Unit to keep things simple.
那是新的一层抽象
That's right a new level of abstraction.
控制单元就像是乐团的指挥
The Control Unit is comparable to the conductor of an orchestra,
指挥着CPU的所有不同组份
directing all of the different parts of the CPU.
完成了一个 检索 破译 执行 循环
Having completed one full fetch/decode/execute cycle,
就可以重头开始 开始检索阶段
we're ready to start all over again, beginning with the fetch phase.
指令地址寄存器的数值是1
The Instruction Address Register now has the value 1 in it,
RAM提供的地址为1的数值是0001 1111
so the RAM gives us the value stored at address 1, which is 0001 1111.
继续到破译阶段
On to the decode phase!
0001是LOAD_B指令 即把RAM的数值传给寄存器B
0001 is the “LOAD_B” instruction, which moves a value from RAM into Register B.
这一次存储器的地址是1111（十进制的15）
The memory location this time is 1111, which is 15 in decimal.
然后到执行阶段
Now to the execute phase!
控制单元配置RAM读取地址15的数值
The Control Unit configures the RAM to read address 15 and
并配置寄存器B接受数据
configures Register B to receive the data.
好 我们就保存了数值00001110（十进制14）进了寄存器B
Bingo, we just saved the value 00001110, or the number 14 in decimal, into Register B.
最后一步是把指令地址寄存器加1
Last thing to do is increment our instruction address register by 1,
这样就完成了又一个循环
and we're done with another cycle.
下一条指令有一些不同
Our next instruction is a bit different.
拿来看看
Let's fetch it.
是1000 01 00
1000 01 00.
操作码1000是加法指令
That opcode 1000 is an ADD instruction.
与4位的RAM地址不同 这条指令用了两组2位数
Instead of an 4-bit RAM address, this instruction uses two sets of 2 bits.
记住2位可以编码4个值
Remember that 2 bits can encode 4 values,
所以2位足够选择4个寄存器了
so 2 bits is enough to select any one of our 4 registers.
第一组2位数是01 这里对应寄存器B
The first set of 2 bits is 01, which in this case corresponds to Register B,
另一组是00 是寄存器A
and 00, which is Register A.
所以1000 01 00是把寄存器B的数值
So “1000 01 00” is the instruction for adding the value in Register B
加到寄存器A里
into the value in register A.
所以要执行这个指令
So to execute this instruction,
需要把第5集的ALU整合到CPU里
we need to integrate the ALU we made in Episode 5 into our CPU.
控制单元负责选择正确的寄存器传递输入（给ALU)
The Control Unit is responsible for selecting the right registers to pass in as inputs,
并配置ALU执行正确的运算
and configuring the ALU to perform the right operation.
这个加法运算中 控制单元开启寄存器B
For this ADD instruction, the Control Unit enables Register B and
把它的数值作为ALU的第一个输入
feeds its value into the first input of the ALU.
同样的开启寄存器A 作为ALU的第二个输入
It also enables Register A and feeds it into the second ALU input.
前面已经提到 ALU可以执行多种运算
As we already discussed, the ALU itself can perform several different operations,
所以控制单元配置它去执行加法运算
so the Control Unit must configure it to perform an ADD operation
通过加法操作码的传递
by passing in the ADD opcode.
最后输出应该存在寄存器A中 但是不能直接写入
Finally, the output should be saved into Register A. But it can't be written directly
因为新的值会再一次传到ALU而一直加下去
because the new value would ripple back into the ALU and then keep adding to itself.
控制单元用一个内部的寄存器临时保存输出
So the Control Unit uses an internal register to temporarily save the output,
关闭ALU再把数值写入合适的目标寄存器
turn off the ALU, and then write the value into the proper destination register.
这里 输入是3和14 因此和是17 或二进制的00010001
In this case, our inputs were 3 and 14, and so the sum is 17, or 00010001 in binary,
这个数储存在了寄存器A中
which is now sitting in Register A.
跟前面一样 最后一步是把指令地址加1
As before, the last thing to do is increment our instruction address by 1,
于是又完成一个循环
and another cycle is complete.
好的 检索最后一个指令
Okay, so let's fetch one last instruction: 01001101.
破译出来可以看到0100是STORE_A指令 附带的RAM地址是13
When we decode it we see that 0100 is a STORE_A instruction, with a RAM address of 13.
跟通常一样 我们把地址传递到RAM模块
As usual, we pass the address to the RAM module,
但不是开启存储器的读取功能 而是写入功能
but instead of read-enabling the memory, we write-enable it.
同时开启寄存器A的读取功能
At the same time, we read-enable Register A.
这样我们就可以用数据线传输寄存器A中的数值
This allows us to use the data line to pass in the value stored in register A.
恭喜 我们刚刚运行完毕了第一个计算机程序
Congrats, we just ran our first computer program!
它载入存储器中的两个数字并相加
It loaded two values from memory, added them together,
然后把和存回存储器
and then saved that sum back into memory.
通过谈论每一步
Of course, by me talking you through the individual steps,
我人工地将CPU在检索 破译和执行阶段中移动
I was manually transitioning the CPU through its fetch, decode and execute phases.
可是计算机里没有迷你的凯莉·安
But there isn't a mini Carrie Anne inside of every computer.
所以让CPU持续行进的任务落到了叫时钟的部件上
So the responsibility of keeping the CPU ticking along falls to a component called the clock.
如它名字所示 时钟以精确而规律的间隔触发电子信号
As it's name suggests, the clock triggers an electrical signal at a precise and regular interval.
控制单元用这个信号提高CPU的内部运算
Its signal is used by the Control Unit to advance the internal operation of the CPU,
保证一切按照时间的规律 像是罗马桨帆船上的人有节奏的击鼓
keeping everything in lock-step - like the dude on a Roman galley drumming rhythmically
在船头上 保证桨手们协调一致 或者类似于节拍器
at the front, keeping all the rowers synchronized... or a metronome.
当然不能行进的太快 因为即使是电流
Of course you can't go too fast, because even electricity takes some time
沿导线传播和信号的确定都需要时间
to travel down wires and for the signal to settle.
CPU运行检索 破译 执行循环中的每一步
The speed at which a CPU can carry out each step of the
的速度叫做时钟速度
fetch-decode-execute cycle is called its Clock Speed.
这一速度用赫兹度量 赫兹是频率的单位
This speed is measured in Hertz - a unit of frequency.
一赫兹意味着每秒一圈循环
One Hertz means one cycle per second.
考虑到我花了6分钟谈论完4个指令
Given that it took me about 6 minutes to talk you through 4 instructions --
载入 载入 加法 储存
LOAD, LOAD, ADD and STORE --
意味着我有效的时钟速度大约是0.03赫兹
that means I have an effective clock speed of roughly 0.03 Hertz.
我承认我不是优秀的计算者 但是即使擅长数学的人
Admittedly, I'm not a great computer but even someone handy with math
可能只能每秒在大脑中计算一次（1赫兹）
might only be able to do one calculation in their head every second or 1 Hertz.
第一个单片的CPU是1971年发行的4位 Intel 4004
The very first, single-chip CPU was the Intel 4004, a 4-bit CPU released in 1971.
它的为结构与我们的示例CPU十分相似
Its microarchitecture is actually pretty similar to our example CPU.
尽管是这类处理器的第一个
Despite being the first processor of its kind,
它有者令人震惊的时钟速度 740千赫兹 每秒74万循环
it had a mind-blowing clock speed of 740 Kilohertz-- that's 740 thousand cycles per second.
你也许觉得很快 但与今天的处理器比微不足道
You might think that's fast, but it's nothing compared to the processors that we use today.
一兆赫兹是每秒一百万时钟循环 你现在看这个视频的
One megahertz is one million clock cycles per second, and the computer or even phone
电脑甚至是手机无疑是几G赫兹
that you are watching this video on right now is no doubt a few gigahertz --
就是每 1 秒几十亿CPU循环
that's BILLIONs of CPU cycles every… single... second.
另外你也许听过调节计算机到超频
Also, you may have heard of people overclocking their computers.
这是调节时钟提高CPU的速度
This is when you modify the clock to speed up the tempo of the CPU --
就像是罗马桨帆船上的鼓手加速擂鼓当需要撞向另一只船时
like when the drummer speeds up when the Roman Galley needs to ram another ship.
芯片制造者一般设给CPU设计对一定的超频足够的容忍度
Chip makers often design CPUs with enough tolerance to handle a little bit of overclocking,
但过度的超频会使CPU过热
but too much can either overheat the CPU,
注：超频通常不会让机箱起火
或是由于信号落后于时钟产生冗余
or produce gobbledygook as the signals fall behind the clock.
尽管你对降频听到的不多 它实际上很有用
And although you don't hear very much about underclocking, it's actually super useful.
有时不必要全速运行处理器
Sometimes it's not necessary to run the processor at full speed...
也许用户离开了计算机 或者运行很费力的程序
maybe the user has stepped away, or just not running a particularly demanding program.
通过降低CPU速度 可以节省很多的能量
By slowing the CPU down, you can save a lot of power,
这对使用电池的计算机 如笔记本和智能机 十分重要
which is important for computers that run on batteries, like laptops and smartphones.
为了满足这些需求 许多现代处理器可以增加或降低时钟速度
To meet these needs, many modern processors can increase or decrease their clock speed
基于不同需求 叫做动态频率调整
based on demand, which is called dynamic frequency scaling.
这样 加上了时钟 CPU就完整了
So, with the addition of a clock, our CPU is complete.
现在可以用盒子封起来 构建成组件
We can now put a box around it, and make it its own component.
没错 新的一层抽象
Yup. A new level of abstraction!
RAM如上一集展示的 在CPU外独立成为一个组件
RAM, as I showed you last episode, lies outside the CPU as its own component,
他们互相通过地址 数据和启动线交流
and they communicate with each other using address, data and enable wires.
虽然我们设计的CPU经过了简化
Although the CPU we designed today is a simplified example,
许多基本的机制仍保留在现代处理器中
many of the basic mechanics we discussed are still found in modern processors.
下一集我们会加强CPU 拓展更多的指令
Next episode, we're going to beef up our CPU, extending it with more instructions as
也将迈入软件大门的第一步
we take our first baby steps into software.
下周见
I'll see you next week.
阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 校：@Auriance 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组